Albert de Rochas Papers 1845-1921 1882-1908 Mss.Ms.Coll.106
American Philosophical Society
Albert de Rochas Papers
Bulk, 1882-1908
1845-1921
Mss.Ms.Coll.106
American Philosophical Society
4.0 Linear feet
A military officer and civilian superintendent of the École Polytechnique in Paris, Albert de Rochas became one of the best known psychic researchers in late nineteenth century France. His interests centered on uncovering the laws behind psychic forces, somnambulism, magnetism and mesmerism, hypnotism, perception, and reincarnation. A prolific writer, he studied a number of Spiritualist and Spiritist mediums, including Maria Mayo (Lina), Eusapia Paladino, and D. D. Home. Despite the relatively small size of the collection, the papers of Albert de Rochas open an important window onto the development of psychic science in fin de siecle France and onto the cultural impact of Spiritualism. The collection includes a scattered, but valuable selection of correspondence with fellow psychic researchers, editors, mediums, and other individuals interested in psychic research, and a valuable set of 69 spirit and psychic photographs, that Rochas collected as evidence of psychic forces, and as documentation of séances, mediums, and "sensitives." Rochas' work on the exteriorization of sensibility and studies of Lina, Charles Bailey, and Paladino are relatively well documented, and his interests in the laws of psychic phenomena, reincarnation, and the exmigration of the living soul run throughout.
Rochas d'Aiglun, Albert de, 1837-1914
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from John Gach Books, 2002.
Scope and Contents note
Despite the relatively small size of the collection, the papers of Albert de Rochas open an important window onto the development of psychic science in fin de siecle France and onto the cultural impact of Spiritualism. The collection includes a scattered, but valuable selection of correspondence with fellow psychic researchers, editors, mediums, and other individuals interested in psychic research, and a valuable set of 69 spirit and psychic photographs, that Rochas collected as evidence of psychic forces, and as documentation of séances, mediums, and "sensitives." Rochas' work on the exteriorization of sensibility and studies of Maria Mayo (Lina), Charles Bailey, and Eusapia Paladino are relatively well documented, and his interests in the laws of psychic phenomena, reincarnation, and the exmigration of the living soul run throughout.
Other aspects of Rochas' career are much less well documented. There is little of family interest in the collection, and only a few items pertaining to his interest in ancient history or engineering. His military career is also poorly documented, although the collection includes a number of letters from former colleagues in the military, some of a personal nature and others relating to military history.
Biographical/Historical note
A military engineer and one of the leading psychic scientists in fin de siècle France, Albert de Rochas was involved in research into a wide range of esoteric topics, from the spirit mediumship of Eusapia Paladino to telepathy and telekinesis, hypnosis, human magnetism, somnambulism, reincarnation, and physical unfolding.
Born into an old Provencal family at Saint Firmin (Haute-Alpes) on May 20, 1837, Rochas entered the Lycée de Grenoble with the intention of studying literature, assuming that he would follow his father and grandfather into the law. When he discovered, however, that the law was less than intellectually stimulating, he switched to mathematics -- a subject at which he excelled -- and set his sights on a career in engineering. After winning the school's prix d'honneur in 1856, he entered the École Polytechnique in Paris to continue his education and to prepare for a career in the military.
In 1861, Rochas was commissioned as Lieutenant de Genie at Montpelier and quickly distinguished himself for his knowledge of the engineering and for his superb administrative abilities. Rising quickly through the ranks to Captain (1864), he was assigned to series of increasingly important assignments after the Franco-Prussian War, culminating in a stint as inspector of studies at the École Polytechnique and a short period as interim director. After earning a promotion to battalion commander in 1880, Rochas was made chief of engineers in 1887 and was given responsibility for updating and strengthening the fortifications around Grenoble.
A scholar at heart, Rochas first became interested in the technology of ancient and medieval engineering while working on the construction of fortifications in the Jura in 1865. His initial attempt at academic writing was a translation of Veterum Mathematicorum Opera (1693), an 11th century Alexandrian treatise on fortification and machines of war, after which he took detours into Hellenism and into the physics and mechanics used by Egyptian priests in constructing their temples. His research and writing were well respected by his scholarly peers, his translations of Greek texts earning him a medal from the Société des Études Grecques.
The work for which Rochas was best known, however, evolved out of an encounter in the mid-1860s with a young man who was susceptible to being magnetized. Even as he plunged into his research on ancient sciences and military history, Rochas applied himself with increasing vigor to the psychic and occult sciences. His first important book on psychic science, Les Forces non Definiés (Paris: Masson, 1887), defined the terms of much of his later research in seeking a scientific basis for occult phenomena. From the mid-1880s into the 1910s, Rochas produced a steady stream of articles and monographs to establish the basic principles behind the exteriorization of sensibility and presented what he was convinced was empirical proof for the existence of a magnetic fluid capable of acting directly on the central nervous system. In 1888, he declined a further promotion in the military to become civilian director at the École Polytechnique, probably because he wished to devote more time to his studies.
Eclectic and evolving, tinged with the Orientalist currents running through contemporary Theosophy and Spiritualism, Rochas touched upon a wide range of topics. Following his widely read work on ancient science, La Science des Philosophes at l'Art des Thaumaturges dans l'Antiquité (Paris: Masson, 1882), he turned to topics such as hypnotism ( L'État Profond de l'Hypnose), death and reincarnation ( Les Vies Successives, 1911; La Suspension de la Vie, 1913), telekinesis ( Extériorisation de la motricité, 1896), and the physical basis of psychic experience ( Les Fluides des Magnétiseurs, 1891; Extériorisation de la Sensibilité, 1895; Les Frontières de la Physique,1898; and Les Frontières de la Science, 1902-1904). He was particularly renowned for a series of experiments conducted with his friends General Thomassin, John Maxwell, De Watteville, and A. de Gramont on the famous Italian medium Eusapia Paladino in which they reported the materialization of spirit hands. His detailed study of the hypnotic subject, Maria Mayo (Mlle Lina), was part of an attempt to assess the influence of music upon human emotions and to measure the human physical response ( Les Sentiments, La Musique, et les Gestes, 1900).
Rochas believed firmly that the scientific study of psychic phenomena would allay people of the fear of death and, by replacing faith with scientifically sound reason, would bring them into closer connection to God. He was named an honorary member of the Académie Delphinale, the Académies of Savoie, Blois, and Aix, and the Sociétéde Psychologie Scientifique of Munich, and was made a Chevalier in the Legion d'Honneur in 1875 and an officer in 1889. He died on September 2, 1914.
Aksakov, Aleksandr, 1832-1903; Bailey, Charles; Besant, Annie Wood, 1847-1933; Buguet, Edouard-Isidore, 1840-; Foras, Eloi Amédée Jacques François, 1830-1899; Hasdeu-Istrati, Bogdan Petriceicu, 1837-1907; Henry, Charles; Lina; Mucha, Alphonse Marie, 1860-1939; Nadar, Félix, 1820-1910; Orléans, Henri Philippe Marie, prince d', 1867-1907; Paladino, Eusapia, 1854-; Pelletier, Horace; Reichel, Willy; Rostoptchine, Lydie, 1837-1915; Schrenck-Notzing, Albert Philibert Franz, 1862-1929; Tissot, James, 1836-1902; Van der Naillen, A. (Albert), 1820-1928; Visani Scozzi, Paolo; Dreams; Ecstasy; Hypnotism; Magnetism; Mediums; Music--Psychological aspects; Parapsychology; Photographs; Psychology--France; Radiographs; Reincarnation; Spirit photography; Spiritism--France; Spiritualism--France; Telepathy; Theosophy; X-rays
- Series I. Correspondence, Bulk, 1882-1908; 1845-1916; 1.25 lin. feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Although incomplete, even fragmentary, Rochas' correspondence touches on a wide range of his interests in psychic research between about 1885 and 1910, including some scarce published articles from the psychic and popular press and several pamphlets on topics of interest. In most cases, correspondents are represented by only one or two letters lacking Rochas' replies. Pieced together, however, these provide an outline of his major research interests and of his connections to other significant psychic researchers in France, Germany, Italy, and elsewhere, such as Albert Philibert Franz Schrenk-Notzing, Willy Reichel, Bogdan Hasdeu-Istrati, and Alexander Aksakoff. Rochas also maintained correspondence with a number of artists and writers, including James Tissot, Alphonse Mucha (although there are no letters from Mucha present).
  Concerned with documenting Spiritualist séances and exploring the underlying basis of psychic phenomena, Rochas received a regular influx of letters from other investigators describing their experiences and experiments. His colleagues kept Rochas informed of the activities of the mediums Eusapia Paladino and Charles Bailey, of research conducted in Italy, France, Germany, Australia, and the United States (see A. Van der Naillen), and there are excellent accounts of experiences with somewhat lesser known operators such as Mme Escalier (see Fernand Boudron), Mme. Adam (see the fascinating 10 page account of psychic occurrences at a seance by Lydie Rostoptchine), Mme Corner, and the Theosophist Mme Blavatsky. More unusual is the letter of M. Lagelouse, who writes that she has been persecuted for eight years, and who sends the names of friends near the moon to vouch for her.
  The Orientalism that marked Spiritualism and Spiritism in the latter decades of the 19th century can be seen throughout the Rochas Papers, not only in the correspondence with or about Theosophists. There are excellent letters on reincarnation from G. Berger, C. Cania, and Annie Besant (the Theosophist), and there is a hint of it in his interest in the possibility of the exmigration of the living soul (see Alexandre Goupil's Cas de vision fantomale and Cas de vision fantomale d'un vivant) and his work on Ecstasy. There is a considerable quantity of material on the sensitive Maria Mayo (Lina) -- Schrenck-Notzing's subject -- and on the physiological effect of music (see e.g. Frandoni Lacombe, Atelier Mucha). Among the miscellaneous items of note are a wonderful letter by the Danish military engineer E. Christmas-Dirckinck-Holmfeld on spirit photography, and a small number of letters from otherwise unidentified persons (e.g. Berthe Dole) who wrote to share their personal psychic experiences.
  - Unidentified author (Box 1)
  - Marie, 1906 Jan. 21; 1 item (Box 1)
    Spirit photography
  - Adam, Mme, 1901 Feb.; 2 items (Box 1)
    Re: Lina
  - Adamovich, Elisabeth, 1903 Dec. 18; 2 items (Box 1)
    Hypnotism and photography. Carte de visite of Adamovich transferred to Ser. II (under Varenik and Vladimirov.
  - Aksakoff, Alexander -- Un cas de dématérialization partielle du corps d'un medium, AMs, 28p. (Box 1)
    Mentions Guppy, Blavatsky, and others
  - Albarracin, Francisco, 1902 April 11; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Wishes to meet to discuss Rochas' psychological studies
  - Anastay, E., 1906 Apr. 29; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Argus de la Presse, 1896, 1905; 2 newsclippings (Box 1)
  - Arnould, Arthur, 1894 Dec. 21; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
    Theosophy
  - Astruc, S., 1889 Dec. 19; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Atelier Mucha -- Premier Essai d'un Ballet: Avec Gestes et Pas Déterminés par les Actions Réflexes de la Musique sur l'Organisme Humain, 1899 Dec. 3; Pr. program, 6p. (Box 1)
    With images taken from Rochas' "Les Sentiments, la Musique et le Geste"
  - Aubry, Desirée, n.d.; PC, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Bader, G., 1897 July 9-17; 2 ALsS (Box 1)
    Mme Eugenie Engel; translation of the Seherin von Prevorst
  - Bailey, Charles -- La Seima et Ame -- W. Britton Harvey, 1908; AMs, 11p. (Box 1)
    Account of Bailey's "Miracles à Melbourne." Includes newspaper clipping "La disavventura del medium Bailey e de' suoi 'ignicolori'" (in Italian).
  - Barrett-Lennard, H., 1900 Jan. 1; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    In English
  - Barruet, Elie, 1900 Feb. 28-1901 Jan. 30; 5 items (Box 1)
  - Bartolomeis, Alissandro, 2 items (Box 1)
    Ghosts of living persons. In Italian
  - Bénezet, Alfred, 1909 Dec. 30-1910 Feb. 11; 4 items (Box 1)
    Mention of Charles Bailey, Aksakoff, Reichel, Fontenay, publications. "Nous continuons ici nos expériences." Dematerialization.
  - Bénezet, Jeannemaire, 1908 Dec. 15-1909 Jan. 5; 3 ALsS (Box 1)
  - Berger, G., n.d.; 2p. (Box 1)
    On Reincarnation.
  - Besant, Annie, 1905 Oct. 7-Nov. 29; 2 ALsS (Box 1)
  - Bodroun, Fernand, 2p. (inc.) (Box 1)
    Instances of "exteriorization of sensibility" in séances with Mme Escalier, Mr. Tayons.
  - Boissans, Archdeacon, n.d.; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
    Photographs and "projections."
  - Boissonet, A., 1902 Aug. 10; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
  - Borie, Albert -- Études physiognomiques [reading notes?], n.d.; AMs, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Bornier, Henri, 1889 May 16; ALS 2p. (Box 1)
    L'Art des Thaumaturges, Magnetism.
  - Bourget, Paul -- Le double de Maupanant, n.d.; AMs, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Breazeale, Guillaume Eugène, 1890 May 19; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    From Belton, South Carolina. Wishes to study mathematics in Europe.
  - Briots, cas aux, 1904 June 7; ALS, 2p. (inc.) (Box 1)
    Experiences with Mme Lay-Fonvieille.
  - Brouardel, P., 1889 Aug. 16; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Cania, C., 1905 Jan. 29; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
    "Si chaque changement de personalité serait un Entité nouvelle qui se présente, vous seriez trompé!" Magnetism, reincarnation.
  - Cahagnet, Alphonse -- Les Arcanes de la Vie Future Dévoilés, n.d.; Printed pam, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Caillard, Paul, 1900-1916; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Calvé, E., n.d.; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Carnot, Adolphe, 1900 Nov. 6; Wedding invtitation (Box 1)
  - Cavaignac, n.d. (Dec. 14); ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Cazaux, Em de, 1896 Dec. 28; ALS, 2p., printed flier (Box 1)
  - Christmas-Dirckinck-Holmfeld, E. de, 1895 Nov. 20; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
    Psychic photography
  - Coillot, Col., 1895 Feb. 9; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Collot, J., 1895 Feb. 8; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Colson, R., 1889 Nov. 17; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Combe, E., 1889 June 3; PC, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Constantin, comte de, 1898 Mar. 8; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Magnetism.
  - Cotes, Jean, 1900 April 11; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
  - Croula, Edward, 1897 June 21; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    "Doubles" of the living.
  - Crozat, Marie de, n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Dame Noire et Dame Blanche, n.d.; Newspaper clipping (Box 1)
  - Dariex, Dr., 1901 Mar. 25; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Sending address of Schrenck-Notzing
  - Debron, Paul, 1900-1901; 7 ALsS (Box 1)
  - De la Crois, J. E., 1890 Jan. 17; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Delanne, G., 1911 Apr. 4; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Denizet, H., 1901 Jult 29; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
  - Des Snart, G. T., n.d.; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
  - Dessin a remettre a Devaux... [dessein d'un echelle double], 1839 June; Tech. drawing (Box 1)
  - Deux Amis arrivent a Mégare..., n.d.; AMs, 33p. (Box 1)
    On telepathy and psychic experiences
  - Doinel, Jules, 1892 Mar. 23; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Dole, Berthe, 1897 July 5-27; 2 ALsS (Box 1)
    Magnetic experiences with her mother and others and practical results.
  - Dolat, M., n.d.; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Donop, 1893 June 3; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Echaguez, F., n.d.; ALS, 6p. (Box 1)
    Interest in psychic experiences. From Spanish Embassy in Paris.
  - L'Écho du Merveilleux 12, no. 277, 1908 July 15; Magazine (Box 1)
  - L'Écho du Merveilleux 13, no. 291, 1909 Feb. 15; Magazine (Box 1)
    Psychic mag. With article by W. T. Stead
  - Ecstase, n.d.; 20 items (Box 1)
    Includes manuscript notes on ecstasy and divination in antiquity and 4 printed articles: "A propos de reves prémonitaires et de paramnésie;" "Faits anormaux;" "De la folie religieuse;" "Phénomenes Mystiques" (from Le Voile d'Isis)
  - Faure-Biguet, P., 1894 Dec.-1904 June 10; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Fernandez, Federico, 1898 Sept. 21; ALS, with trans. (Box 1)
    In Spanish, from Sec. of the Argentine Theosophical Society
  - Fevrier, J., 1890 Aug. 12; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Flamion, J., 1897 Feb. 16; ALS, 5p. (Box 1)
    Psychic experiences.
  - Flammarion, Sylvie, 1893 Jan. 22; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
  - Fontenay, Guillaume de, 1910 Jan. 2-Feb. 11; 2 ALsS (Box 1)
    Mentions Bailey and Richet.
  - Foras, Eloi Amédée Jacques François de, 1876 Dec. 19; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Foudrier, Adrien, 1849 Oct. 16; ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Gaillard, M. -- Oisivetés de M. Vauban (Paris: J. Corréard, 1845), Pam., 137p.: ill. (Box 1)
    With extra sheets from "Sur l'usage que l'on peut faire des Galères en Bretagne."
  - Gacogne, E., n.d.; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Gobers, F., 1891 Jan. 30; ALS, 3p. (Box 1)
    Military service in Poland, Russia.
  - Goupil, Alexandre[?], 1909 Aug. 1; ALS and enclosure (Box 1)
    Encloses "Cas de vision fantomale" and "Cas de vision fantomale d'un vivant."
  - Gordon-Setter-Club -- Programme et Reglement des Field-Trials de 1891, Pam., 8p. (Box 1)
    Paul Caillard, President
  - Grandhauy, Gerard, 1888 Nov. 24; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Gramont, A., n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Haemmerle, Agathe, 1902 June 6; ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
  - Hasdeu-Istrati, Bogdan Petriceicu, 1895 Aug. 12-1899 Feb. 14; 2 ALsS (Box 1)
    See Series II for photographs enclosed.
  - Havet, L., 1882 Feb. 2; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Henderson, E., 1890 Jan. 29; ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
  - Henry, Charles -- Application de Nouveaux Instruments de Précision... à l'Archéologie (Paris: Ernest Leroux, 1890), Pam., 31p. (Box 1)
  - Henry, Charles -- Le Livre de l'Avenir, n.d.; Newspaper clipping (Box 1)
  - Henry, Charles -- Sur une Loi Générale des Réactions Psycho-Motrices (Paris: Assoc. Française des Sciences, 1888), 1889; Pam., 37p. (Box 1)
  - Hübbe-Scheliden, Wilhelm, 1901 Apr. 14; PC, 1p. (Box 1)
  - Ille[?], Ch. d', 1909 Oct. 14; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Joire, Paul -- "Étude de Psychologie Musicale, L'Expression Pure des Sentiments et des Passions", n.d.; 8p. (Box 2)
    With photos of Lina
  - Kardec, Allan -- Phénomènes Spirites Observés auGroupe Amitié de Lyon de 1884 à 1890 (Tours, 1895), Pam, 29p. (Box 2)
  - Keil, Alfred, 1903 May 25; ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Kjellman, F., 1889 Aug. 21; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Human magnetism.
  - Labadye, cte de, n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Lacombe, Mad. Frandoni, ALS, 7p. (Box 2)
    Music and the sentiments.
  - Lacoste, 1893 Aug. 10; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Laffaut, C., 1889 May 9; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Lagelouse, M., 1903 Mar. 10; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Has been persecuted for eight years; sends names of friends near the moon to vouch for her.
  - Lamontas, Marie de, n.d.; 5 ALsS (Box 2)
  - Langalerud, G. de, 1890 Feb. 2, 22; 2 ALsS (Box 2)
  - Le Bon, Gustave, n.d.; Pr. Invitation (Box 2)
  - Lemoine, Emile, n.d.; ANS, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Lina, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Folder 1, 1884; 2 items (Box 2)
      Lina M. was a young woman with whom, Schrenk-Notzing conducted experiments in thought transferrance. Includes pam: Premier Essay d'un Ballet and copy of Bulletin de l'Imprimerie et de la Librarie, Oct. 25, 1884.
    - Folder 2, 1901 Nov. 4; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
      Includes 4 other items of uncertain relationship foldered together.
  - Linder, 1894 Mar. 10; ALS with encl. (Box 2)
    Encloses letter to Linder
  - Magnin, Emile, 1904-1905; 5 items (Box 2)
    Includes 2 ALsS, PC, and 2 pams: "'Magdeleine' Étude sur le Geste au Moyen de l'Hypnose" and "De l'Interprétation artistique" (with photos of Lina).
  - Marie(?), 1906 Jan. 21; ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Dariex has recommended Rochas as the person to give permission to reproduce photographs of "doubles." Author is editor of Nice Illustré.
  - Les Matérialisations, 1906; Pr.Ms, 18p. (Box 2)
  - Maugin, L.(?), 1888 Nov. 9; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Maurice, C., 1900 July 10; ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Maxwell, Joseph, 1905, 1910; 2 items (Box 2)
    Includes copy of Maxwell's pam. Sur les Phénomènes de Hantise (Paris, 1905).
  - Mesnard, H., 1911 Mar. 28; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Sending a photograph taken by new process. Includes note and envelope that may not be related.
  - Meyerson, Émile -- Les Travaux de M. Charles Henry sur une Théorie Mathématique de l'Expression (Paris: Armand Collin, 1890), Pam., 5p. (Box 2)
  - Montorsaux, Georges, n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Moskvitissoff, Barbe de, 1897 Apr. 15; ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
  - Moulins, L., n.d.; ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Néon, Françcois de -- De Françcois de Néon, Courrier de Paris, Sue le Sueil du Mystère, n.d.; AMs, 6p. (Box 2)
  - Occultism, notes, n.d.; AMs, 14 items (Box 2)
  - Occultisme Pratique, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 6p. (Box 2)
  - Olivier, Emile, 1894 July 12; AMsS Poem, 3p. (Box 2)
  - Orléans, Henri Philippe Marie, prince d', n.d.; 5 items (Box 2)
    Includes 3 ALsS, newspaper clipping on Orleans, and calling card for Robert d'Orleans. Mentions Eusapia Paladino.
  - Peaucellier, Gen., 1888 Sept. 26; Pr. Circ. LS, 3p. (2 cies) (Box 2)
  - Pelletier, Horace, 1888-1890; 6 ALsS (Box 2)
    Spiritualism and spiritualists
  - Perneuil, C. de., 1895-1897; 2 ALsS (Box 2)
  - Perrin, Maurice-Henri, 1906 Apr. 7; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Perrot, G., 1887 May 30; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Pfeifer, Xaver -- "Des Goldenen Schnittes," Sphinx 4, 24 (1887): 369 ff., Pr. M, 28p. (Box 2)
    In German
  - Pierrou(?), Gen., n.d.; 3 ALsS (Box 2)
  - Pillot, J., n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Pinot, Anna, 1893 May 22; ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
  - Piore, L. C. Em., 1898 Apr. 22; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Polosoff, N. de, 1889 Aug. 16; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Pont, Abbé de -- Réflexions à Propos des Origines du Patois de la Tarentaise (Paris, 1872), Pam., 24p. (Box 2)
  - A Propos de Rachel, n.d.; AMs, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Reboux, Paul (?) -- Instinct des animaux, n.d.; AMs, 6p. (Box 2)
    With newspaper clipping signed by Reboux.
  - Recherches expérimentales au sujet du Fantôme des Vivants, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 18p. (Box 2)
  - Reichel, Willy, 1909-1910; 18 items (Box 2)
    Includes letter from Charles Bailey, T. Thomassins, H. Beckh
  - [Reichel, Willy]. Le Professeur Willy Reichel, 1909; AMs, 11p. (Box 2)
  - Ripault, A., 1897 Oct. 10; ALS, 4p., encl. (Box 2)
  - Revue Ampère 2 (1901), Pam. (Box 2)
  - Revue Suisse des Sciences Psychiques 1 (1913), Pam., 32p. (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert [Biographical entry in Dictionnaire Biographique Internationale des écrivains des Artistes...], Pr. Ms, p.53-56 (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- Les Doctrines Chimiques au XVIIe Siècle (Paris, 1888), Pam., 13p. (Box 2)
    Includes loose illus. showing points of connection between points on the face and parts of the body and newspaper clipping "Malades et médecins -- Curieuse étude de M. Albert de Rochas," Sept. 27, 1890.
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Enrégistrement photographique des êtres et radiations de l'espace," Lumière no. 329 (1908), Pam. (2 copies), 8p. (Box 2)
    Reprint.
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- Les expériences très intéressants de M. de Rochas..., n.d.; AMs, 13p. (Box 2)